Guide to the Arthur Garfield Kennedy Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Arthur Garfield Kennedy papers
1903-1954
SC0044
Kennedy, Arthur Garfield, 1880-1954.
13.5 Linear feet
Personal and professional correspondence, notes, reviews, notebooks, bibliography of writings on the English language, and other papers. Material relates to specific works of Dr. Kennedy on English philology and current use of English, Stanford University during World War II, scholarly groups to which Kennedy belonged, Stanford groups, and official Stanford agencies. Correspondents include Hardin Craig,, Helge Kökeritz, Lucia B. Mirrieless, Clark S. Northrup, Louise Pound, John S. P. Tatlock and Philip Sheridan.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Kennedy family, 1968.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Professor of English Philology at Stanford (1914-1945; emeritus 1945-1954) and Chairman of the English Department (1941-1945).
Arthur Garfield Kennedy was born on June 29, 1880, in Weeping Water, Nebraska. He received his A.B. from Doane College in 1902, and his A.M. degree from the University of Nebraska in 1905. He taught high school English and German until 1912 at which time he came to Stanford where he received his Ph.D. in English Philology in 1914. He began his career of teaching at Stanford in 1914 as an instructor, and advanced steadily in the department to the rank of Professor of English Philology in 1929. From 1941 until his retirement in 1945 he was executive head of the department. He died on April 21, 1954.
Dr. Kennedy's several books include a Bibliography of Writings on the English Language(1927); A Concordance to the Complete Works of Chaucer, with J.S.P. Tatlock (1927); Current English (1935); English Usage (1940); and A Concise Bibliography for Students of English (1940)
The contents of this collection consists primarily of Dr. Kennedy's correspondence with academic colleagues, though some personal letters are included. Of special interest is his wartime correspondence with Philip Sheridan, one of his graduate students, which contains accounts of Stanford and the English department during the war years. Also included in the collection are materials dealing with Dr. Kennedy's various published works, copie sof his earliest publications on grammar, some grade books from his years as a teacher, and copies of A concise Bibliography for Students of English and Bibliography of Writings on the English Language.
Description of the Collection
Personal and professional correspondence, notes, reviews, notebooks, bibliography of writings on the English language, and other papers. Material relates to specific works of Dr. Kennedy on English philology and current use of English, Stanford University during World War II, scholarly groups to which Kennedy belonged, Stanford groups, and official Stanford agencies. Correspondents include Hardin Craig,, Helge Kökeritz, Lucia B. Mirrieless, Clark S. Northrup, Louise Pound, John S. P. Tatlock and Philip Sheridan.
Access Terms
Craig, Hardin, 1875-1968.; Kennedy, Arthur Garfield, 1880-1954.; Kökeritz, Helge.; Mirrielees, Lucia B.; Northrup, Clark S.; Pound, Louise, 1872-1958.; Sheridan, Philip.; Stanford University. Department of English. Faculty.; Tatlock, John S. P.; English literature--Study and teaching.; World War, 1939-1945--California--Stanford.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Correspondence A – C. Includes among miscellaneous correspondence letters from:
    - Ackermann, Robert W., 1947-50, re An Index of Arthurian Names in Middle English (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Alden, Raymond and Donald, 1930-? (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bailey, Margery re request for recommendations, 1920-1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bonner, Willard D. re conditions in graduate department of English as that time, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Briggs, William D. and wife, 1928-1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bryan, W. F., re bibliography of the English language, 1921-1927 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Burt, Thomas G. re Kennedy's membership in Phi Beta Kappa, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Carruth, W. H. including a report on the Chaucer dictionary, 1915-1919 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Craig, Hardin, 1922-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Craigie, W. A., 1925-1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Curry, Walter C., 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence D – G. Includes among miscellaneous correspondence letters from:
    - Doane College, 1932-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Elsasser, Albert, 1935-1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Farnham, O. E. re Rose Bowl, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Flügel, Felix re gift of his father's papers (see also, folder on Chaucer Concordance), 1925-1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Greaves, John re spelling reform, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence H – K. Includes among miscellaneous correspondence letters from:
    - Hanley, Miles, L. re Hempl papers, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Harrer, Charlotte Forster, 1936, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Hartwig, George H., 1934-1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Hoover, Herbert re faculty opinion at Stanford (2 letters), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Ichikawa, Sanki re membership in English Literary society of Japan, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Jordan, Mrs. David Starr, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Kenyon, John S., 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Kokeritz, Helge, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence L – P. Includes among miscellaneous correspondence letters from:
    - Lindberg, J. C., 1927 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Lipman, Charles B., Univ. of California re departmental rating, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Loomis, Roger S., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Magoun, Francis P., 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Meritt, Herbert Dean re "Old English Glosses" report, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Mirrielees, Lucia B., 1927-1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Northrup, Clark S. re Von Patten conflict (see also Middle English Dictionary folder), 1925-1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Pound, Louise, 1928-1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence R – S. Includes among miscellaneous correspondence letters from:
    - Sato, Masaru, 1949-1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Shearin, Mrs. Hubert G. re Dr. Shearin's papers, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Stegner, Wallace, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Philip Sheridan, 1943-1946
    - Philip Sheridan was a graduate student of Prof. Kennedy whose studies were interrupted by World War II. Dr. Kennedy's letters deal extensively with Stanford, in general, and the Department of English, in particular, during the war years. (for more Sheridan material, see also SC 255 John McClelland Papers) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence T – Z. Includes among miscellaneous correspondence letters from:
    - Tatlock, John S. P. (see also, folder on Chaucer Concordance), 1915-1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Taylor, W. A. re academic standards for graduation, 1924-1932 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Tucker, Gilbert M., 1923 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Vizetelly, Dr. Frank H., 1924-1926, re Funk and Wagnalls Dictionaries (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Wintors, Ivor, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Zandvoort, R. W., 1927-1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Academic Associations, membership in and correspondence with:
    - American Association of University Professors (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - California Writers Club (see correspondence with Katharine Bennett) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Linquistic Society of America (see correspondence with Aurelio M. Espinosa) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Mediaeval Academy of America (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Middle English Language and Literature (see correspondence with A. C. Baugh) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Modern Language Association of America (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Phi Beta Kappa (see corespondence with Thomas G. Burt) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Simplified Spelling Association (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Family affairs and correspondence:
    - Letters, genelaogical references, family business, 1928-1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Also, Palo Alto concerns. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Office of the President, Stanford University, official correspondence with:
    - Administrative actions relating both to the English Department as a whole and to Dr. Kennedy in particular – salary, departmental organization, academic council, parking problems, etc., 1917-1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Stanford Groups and Organizations, membership in and correspondence with:
    - Academic Council (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Fellowhip Forum (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - The Research Club of Stanford University (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Residents Club of Palo Alto (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Stanford Faculty Club (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Stanford Library Association (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - American Speech:
    - American Speech was a "quarterly of linguistic usage" to which Dr. Kennedy often contributed reveiws and articles. This folder contains correspondence with W. Cabell Greet, long-time editor of the magazine, material relating to the bibliography of American Speech, and other letters and material relating to the quarterly. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Bibliographical Guides for the Study of English, 1931
    - Reviews, letters requesting copies, critical comments by colleagues (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - A Bibliography of Writings on the English Language, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Letters requesting copies, critical comments by colleagues (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - A Concise Bibliography for Students of English, Systematically Arranged; 2nd ed, 3rd ed.:, 1940, 1954
    - Copy of "Forward," clipping of review, Kennedy's directions to the editor, notes involved in the Bibliography's preparation, critical comments by colleagues (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - A Concordance to the Complete Works of Geoffrey Chaucer and to the Raumont of the Rose:, 1927
    - Letter to the President of the Carnegie Institution (1916) on "history, present state, and prospects of the Chaucer concordance," correspondence with John S. P. Tatlock concerning the book, copy of "Instructions to collaborators," copy of "Chaucer research in progress in 1941," list of contents of various boxes of materials ready for printing (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Current English, 1935
    - Letters requesting copies, correspondence with the publisher, ciritical comments from colleagues (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - English Usage, 1942
    - Notes involved in preparation of English Usage, correspondence with the publishers, critical comments from colleagues, clipping of a review of the book (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - The Middle English Dictionary:
    - Correspondence with Clark Northrup, editor, and with others concerned in the publication; copy of "Observations concerning a standardized spelling for the main entries in the MED;" copy of "an announcement of the Middle English dictionary;" copy of the reprint, The Middle English Dictionary, L-Laik; minutes of the committee on the English Period Dictionaries (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Thorndike-Barnhart Junior and Collegiate Dictionaries:
    - Comments made by Kennedy in his capacity as a member of the editorial board, and other correspondence with the publisher, 1936-1942 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - J. C. Lindberg and A. G. Kennedy. An Outline of English Grammar, 1st and rev. eds, 1908, 1910 (Box 2)
  - J. C. Lindberg and A. G. Kennedy. English Grammar for Secondary Schools, Parts I and II, 1911 (Box 2)
  - Grade books from Dr. Kennedy's years as a teacher, 1903, 1906, 1909, 1938 (Box 2)
  - A. G. Kennedy. A Bibliography of Writings on the English Language; from the beginnnings of printing to the end of 1922. Harvard University Press, 1927 (Box 2)
  - A. G. Kennedy. A Concise Bibliography for Students of English, Systematically Arranged. Stanford University Press, 1940 (Box 2)
  - Notebook #1, Volume I. Materials pertaining to The Anglo-Saxon Reader, circa 1929
    - Correspondence with George Philip Krapp, co-author of the Anglo-Saxon Reader, 1924-1930 (Box 3A)
    - Correspondence with Henry Holt and Co., Inc., 1927-1930 (Box 3A)
    - critical comments and suggestions by academic colleagues, undated (Box 3A)
    - Contents also include sample tables of contents, notes and plans used in organizations of the materials, examples of slips used in glossary, and tables of materials, undated (Box 3A)
  - Notebook #2, Volume I. Materials pertaining to Bibliography of Writings on the English Language c. 1927 (1st of 2 notebooks), 1919-1925
    - Correspondence with Harvard University Press and Yale University Press, joint publishers, 1924-1925 (Box 3A)
    - Critical comments and suggestions by academic colleagues, 1919-1925 (Box 3A)
    - 2 letters from Ray Lyman Wilbur, polite inquiries about Dr. Kennedy's progress on his book, 1921, 1923 (Box 3A)
    - Contents also include copy of a paper on need for a bibliography of the English language read at a meeting of the Philological Association of the Pacific Coast, Nov. 28, 1919; reprint of "A Bibliography of the Enlgish Language" appearing in the Correspondence section of Modern Language Notes; samples of prefaces; list of periodicals to be used in work on the Bibliography; table of contents; typographical notes; note to the editor and/or proofreader; and rules for Index., 1924-1925 (Box 3A)
  - Notebook #3, Volume II. Materials pertaining to Bibliography of Writings on the English Language c. 1927 (2nd of 2 notebooks), 1926-1935
    - Correspondence with Harvard University Press and Yale University Press, joint publishers, 1926-1931 (Box 3A)
    - Critical comments and suggestions by academic colleagues, 1926-1935 (Box 3A)
    - 2 letters from Ray Lyman Wilbur congratulating Kennedy on his book, undated (Box 3A)
    - Correspondence from academic colleagues re A Concordance to the Complete Works of Geoffrey Chaucer, 1927 (Box 3A)
    - Contents also include: copy of "A Biblopgraphy of Writings on the English Language from the Beginning of Printing to the end of 1922," a note to appear in the Fall Announcement, 1926, Harvard University Press; paper, "The Making of a Bibliography" (not further identified); review list for book; notes to the editor about corrections; and royalty statements. (Box 3A)
  - Notebook #4, Volume I. Materials pertaining to Current English (1st of 2 notebooks), -1935
    - Correspondence Correspondence with Ginn and Co., publishers, 1932-1934 (Box 3A)
    - Criticisms and suggestions re manuscript from academic colleagues (Box 3A)
    - Letters to various publishers requesting permission to use copyrighted materials (Box 3A)
    - Contents also include: Agenda (Kennedy's schedule for work on the book); lists of errata; tenative plan of book; sample table of contents; copy of statement of plans and goals--"A Select Bibliography of Writings on Modern English"; pagination of first draft; typed comments requested by Ginn and Co. from four authorities in the field; and rejected portions of the manuscript. (Box 3A)
  - Notebook #5, Volume II. Materials pertaining to Current English(2nd of 2 notebooks), circa 1935 1934-1947
    - Correspondence with Ginn and Co., 1934-1947 (Box 3A)
    - Critical comments and suggestions by academic colleagues (Box 3A)
    - Contents also include: copy of pamphlet in memory of Roswell Thornton Pearl (1887-1934), one of Ginn's editors; copies of announcement of book and advertising circulars; list of periodicals for review; notes and instructions to the editors and/or proofreaders; and clipping of review in the San Francisco Examiner. (Box 3A)
  - English Language & Literature, Part i, chap. 1-199, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - English Language & Literature, Part i, chap. 200-end, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - English Language & Literature, Part ii, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - English Language & Literature, Part iii, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - English Language & Literature, Part iv, div. 2, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - English Language & Literature, Part iv, div. 7-10, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - English Language & Literature, Part v, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - English Language & Literature, Part vi, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - English Language & Literature, Part vii, chap. 1-124, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - English Language & Literature, Part vii, chap. 130-end, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - English Language & Literature, Part viii, chap. 1-99, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - English Language & Literature, Part viii, chap. 100-end, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - English Language & Literature, Part ix, chap. 1-20, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - English Language & Literature, Part ix, chap. 21-24, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - English Language & Literature, Part ix, chap. 25-28, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - English Language & Literature, Part ix, chap. 28-42, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - English Language & Literature, Part ix, chap. 43-end, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - English Language & Literature, Part x, chap. 1-99, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - English Language & Literature, Part x, chap. 100-114, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - English Language & Literature, Part x, chap. 117-139, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - English Language & Literature, Part x, chap. 148-161, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - English Language & Literature, Part x, chap. 162-200, undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - English Language & Literature, Part x, chap. 200-274, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - English Language & Literature, Part x, chap. 275-324, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - English Language & Literature, Part x, chap. 325-400, undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - English Language & Literature, Part x, chap. 400-466, undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - English Language & Literature, Part x, chap. 500-600, undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - English Language & Literature, Part x, chap. 600-699, undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - English Language & Literature, Part x, chap. 700-899, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - English Language & Literature, Part x, chap. 900-999, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - English Language & Literature, Part xi, chap. 1-199, undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - English Language & Literature, Part xi, chap. 200-end, undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - English Language & Literature, Part xii-xiii, undated (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - English Language & Literature, Part xiv, chap. 1-313, undated (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - English Language & Literature, Part xiv, chap. 316-799, undated (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - English Language & Literature, Part xv, undated (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - English Language & Literature, Part xvi, chap. 1-12, undated (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - English Language & Literature, Part xvi, chap. 14-20, undated (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - English Language & Literature, Part xvi, chap. 17-25, undated (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - English Language & Literature, Part xvi, chap. 100-128, undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - English Language & Literature, Part xvi, chap. 130, undated (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - English Language & Literature, Part xvi, chap. 132-140, undated (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - English Language & Literature, Part xvi, chap. 140-144, undated (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - English Language & Literature, Part xvi, chap. 140:42-144, undated (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - English Language & Literature, Part xvi, chap. 200-220, undated (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - English Language & Literature, Part xvi, chap. 230-265, undated (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - English Language & Literature, Part xvi, chap. 300-end, undated (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - English Language & Literature, Part xvii, chap. All, undated (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - English Language & Literature, Part xviii, chap., undated (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - English Language & Literature, Part xix-xx, undated (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - English Language & Literature, Part xivv, undated (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Kennedy, A. G.; Library notes; Book 1 100-400, undated (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Kennedy, A. G.; Library notes; Book 2 500-990, undated (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Kennedy, A. G.; A New Cook at Our House Or... Book I, undated (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Kennedy, A. G.; Humor and Journalism Book II verse, undated (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Modern English Verse, Book II, verse Bk I, undated (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Modern English Verse, Book III, verse Bk II, undated (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - The Short Story; Book V, undated (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Miscellaneous (II), Book VII, undated (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Miscellaneous Prose, Book VIII, undated (Box 6, Folder 60)